绝不手下留情!
There will be no mercy!
我妹妹的独子正被钉在十字架上!
My sister's only child hanging from a cross!
- 约瑟...  - 我们需要的是结束这一切!
- Joseph...  - We need this to end!
我们要根据我们的法律来管理自己
We must govern ourselves
这样我们将不再受到罗马法律的制裁
so that we are never again subjected to Roman justice.
你一点有用的事也没做
You did nothing of any worth whatsoever.
给安提帕王让路
Make way for King Antipas.
你的地位仰赖于我的认可
Your position is reliant on my endorsement.
约翰 我有着同样贫苦的灵魂
John, I'm poor and sick in my soul.
很高兴现在送给了你们这块地
I'm glad to give you this land.
巴拿巴 再好不过了
Barnabas, it's perfect.
神给我们每个人都有旨意 我应该去传道
God has a purpose for each of us. I'm meant to preach.
耐心点 司提反 时机会到的
Be patient, Stephen. The time will come.
难道耶稣没有在你将他处死而他又复活前说过
And didn't Jesus say, "I will rebuild this temple in three days"
"我能拆毁神的殿"吗?!
before he rose from the death you condemned him to?
让他安静 让他闭嘴
Silence him. Shut him up.
求主耶稣接收我的灵魂
Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第6集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 影子
翻译: 飘飘行天下 小黄不小黄
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
"你地上不再听见强暴的事
"No longer will violence be heard in your lands,
境内不再听见荒凉毁灭的事
nor ruin and destruction within your borders.
你必称你的墙为拯救
Your walls shall be called salvation,
称你的门为赞美
and your gates praise.
日头不再作你白昼的光
No longer will the sun light your days
月亮也不再发光照耀你
nor the moon bright your night.
耶和华却要作你永远的光
You will have the Lord for everlasting light
你神要为你的荣耀"
and your God for your glory."
我的儿子死了! 司提反死了!
My son is dead! Stephen is dead!
都是因为你! 你和你的政治斗争!
Because of you! You and your politics!
他在哪儿?
Where is he?
你的弥赛亚如今又在哪儿!
Where is he now, this Messiah of yours?
为什么他不叫司提反从死里复活
Why doesn't he raise him up
或是让主把司提反带回我们身边?
or ask the Lord to bring Stephen back to us?
是为了我们而试验他吗?
Is it for us to test him?
我昨晚梦见
I dreamt last night
还会有人像司提反一样牺牲
that Stephen wouldn't be the last of us to die.
又一个听了道的饥渴的灵魂
Another hungry soul that's heard the word.
愿神与你同在
God be with you.
你是来听耶稣的道吗?
Have you come to hear the word of Jesus?
不是
No.
我名叫扫罗
I am Saul.
我是名学者 犹太人 罗马公民 法利赛人
Scholar, Jew, Roman citizen, Pharisee,
耶路撒冷伟大神殿的保卫者
defender of the great temple of Jerusalem.
我是来教你们一个道理
I have come to teach you of the wrath
若你们不停止那些亵渎神灵的话
you will all bring down upon yourselves
会有什么样的震怒降临到你们身上
if you do not end your blasphemy.
如若不然
If.
旷野和干旱之地必然欢喜
The desert and the parched land will be glad.
沙漠也必快乐...
The wilderness will rejoice...
又像玫瑰开花
and blossom; Like the crocus,
必开花繁盛
it will burst into bloom.
乐上加乐...
It will rejoice greatly...
而且欢呼
and shout for joy.
那么 跟我们说说
So, tell us,
我们的信念到底有什么错?
how are we so wrong in our belief?
朋友 说话呀
Friend, speak with us.
怎么了 你是没有舌头吗?
What's the matter, have you no tongue?
还是没有脑子?
Or no brain?
拿撒勒人耶稣
Jesus of Nazareth,
你们喜爱并赞美的这个乡巴佬弥赛亚
this peasant Messiah you love and praise,
不过就是个假先知而已
is nothing more than a false prophet.
你竟敢来这里说这番话?
You dare come here and say that?
不是我说的 是犹太公会说的
I don't say it. The Sanhedrin says it.
是所罗门王的诗章里说的
The psalms of Solomon say it.
是耶利米书 以赛亚书和但以理书里的预言说的
The prophecies of Jeremiah, Isaiah, and Daniel say it.
要不然又该是谁说的呢?
Who are you to say otherwise?
谁?
Who?
哦
Oh.
怎么了?
What's the matter?
你没有舌头吗?
Have you no tongue?
还是没有胆子?
No courage?
走开吧 矮子
Be gone, little man.
我不明白 约拿单
I don't understand you, Jonathan.
你看见了那场大屠杀 一波接一波的十字架刑罚
You saw the slaughter, the wave of crucifixions,
也见识了耶路撒冷城里一刻不停的骚乱
saw what bloody turmoil made its home in Jerusalem.
当然 父亲 我又不是瞎子
Of course. Father, I'm not blind.
那你还接受作为一个大祭司 该亚法居然
And you accept that Caiaphas, as high priest,
任由血流成海
stands knee-deep in blood.
这是彼拉多手持罗马权利之剑所杀出的一片血海
Blood spilled by Pilate wielding the power of Rome.
诚然 我认为该亚法没处理好这件事
Yes, I accept Caiaphas has not handled things well.
那你为什么不同意必须找人取代他?
So, why can't you accept that he must be replaced?
耶路撒冷需要有个人
Jerusalem needs a man who will forge
能和罗马帝国建立起全新的关系
a different relationship with Rome
能带领我们重回该亚法曾经代表的
to take us back to the peaceful times
和平年代
Caiaphas once stood for.
犹太公会在找人取代该亚法的地位
The Sanhedrin is looking for a man to challenge Caiaphas.
我们亚那家族希望这个人是你
The Annas family needs that man to be you.
让你亲爱的一家人
The whole idea of your loving family
都聚到我们家里来祈祷感恩
gathered in our house to give thanks
这件事恕我无法理解
gives me indigestion.
喝点药 清醒下头脑
Well, take a potion. Clear your head.
两位尊贵的客人不请自来了
Two guests of honor have invited themselves.
其实早一点通知我们也没什么坏处
Although a little more notice wouldn't have hurt.
安提帕和希罗底
Antipas and Herodias.
我不知道拿撒勒人的营地
I had no idea the Nazarene camp
居然离城里这么近
was so close to the city.
还这么繁荣
And so populated.
怎么会有人抛弃熟悉的一切
Why would anyone leave everything they knew
去过这样的生活?
to live like that?
因为普珥节您能光临寒舍
We are honored the festival of Purim
我们倍感荣幸
has brought you to our home.
确实 用这作为来耶路撒冷的借口倒是挺有用
In truth, it was a useful excuse to come to Jerusalem.
来看看这座城是否还屹立不倒
To see if the city was still standing.
我的儿子和我觉得
My son and I think,
同为犹太人 我们可以开诚布公地谈谈最近这段黑暗的时期
as Jews, we can talk honestly about recent dark days.
人民没法很快淡忘彼拉多巡抚
The people will not soon forget the blood spilled
在多起十字架刑罚中屠杀的人命
in Governor Pilate's wave of crucifixions.
他们也不应该忘记
They shouldn't forget.
但是真的有某个时期人民是心满意足的吗?
But was there ever a time when the people were content?
要是民众的怒火减息
If the anger of the people was fading,
那你们这种自鸣得意的处理方式就还有用
there would be room for this complacent approach.
父亲 我们几乎从未自鸣得意
Father, we are hardly complacent.
但是怒火是在增长
But the anger is growing,
就好像沙漠里新兴的帐篷城市在增长一样
just as the new city of tents out in the desert is growing.
- 你是说那个营地吗?  - 唔
- You mean the camp?  - Hm.
那里现在有数千之众了吧
There are thousands there now.
没错
Yes.
我们在来的路上经过了
We passed it on our way here.
人多到什么时候才会停止?
Where will it stop?
五千教徒?
At 5,000 converts?
还是一万?
100,000?
大家能不能别再
Will everybody please stop
谈论那些人了?
going on about these people?
说吧 你们究竟想让我干什么?
Tell me, what exactly is it that you'd have me do?
嗯?
Hmm?
把他们在帐篷里就地屠杀?
Have them slaughtered in their tents?
安提帕 诚然人民...
Antipas, surely, the people...
以及作为他们统治者的您...
and you, as their ruler...
想要看到一个能控制事态发展
want to see a high priest in control of events.
而不是随波逐流的大祭司
Not led by them.
不是罗马大人一声令下 就言听计从的大祭司
Not governed by the whim of his Roman master.
我确实很享受空气中弥漫的背叛的硝烟
I do enjoy the smell of treachery.
可怜的老该亚法看起来就像
Poor old Caiaphas has the look of a man
马上要上刑场一样
preparing to face the executioner.
如果要在
If it was a choice
他和年轻的约拿单中选一个做大祭司
between him and young Jonathan as high priest,
我还真不知道我选谁好
I don't know who I'd go for.
两个都不想选
Neither.
但我不得不支持其中一个
But I'll have to give my support to one of them,
然后让彼拉多担起责任来
and then let Pilate have the responsibility.
夫人请
My lady.
后来有个叫撒迦利的别是巴人
And then there was Zachary of Beersheba,
一个满怀激情的人 想要遵循
a passionate man who tried to follow
摩西的先例
the example of Moses
带领他的朋友们穿过红海
and lead his friends across the red sea.
他淹死了 他们也淹死了
He drowned, and so did they.
后来又有个从佩里亚来的西门...
And then there was Simon from Peraea...
大胆勇敢 用心良苦的西门
Brave, well-intentioned Simon.
他坚信他是神派来的
Well, he believed that he was sent by God
结果却让犹太人的生活...
but only made a Jew's life ha...
却让犹太人的生活比在罗马统治下更不堪
But only made a Jew's life harder under Rome.
后来还有一个装模作样的人...
And there was another pretender...
一个从加利利来的骗子 叫耶稣的人
An imposter from Galilee, this man Jesus.
你就是彼得 我听过你传道
You're Peter. I've heard you preach.
讲得不错
You do it well.
可能有点过于仁慈 不过...
A little softhearted, perhaps, but...
我有充分的理由反对你们那个假冒的弥赛亚!
I have a case to make against your false Messiah!
你想听听看吗 彼得
Do you want to hear it, Peter,
还是你怕我在这群容易受骗的信众前
or are you afraid I will unpick your delusions
戳穿你的谎言?
in front of this gullible crowd?
这个人活在黑暗中
This man is living in darkness
竟不知自己的眼是闭着的
and doesn't even know his eyes are closed.
他宣扬这些话
He claims such knowledge,
却不过是在黑暗中蹒跚而行
but he's just stumbling in the dark
如果他不明白...
if he doesn't know this...
不靠着耶稣 谁也无法进到父面前
no one can come to the father except through Jesus.
耶稣便是那路 是真理 是生命
Jesus is the way and the truth and the life.
你们那个耶稣
This Jesus of yours
不过是个目不识丁的渔夫
is nothing more than a false prophet
冒充先知
of illiterate fishermen.
他让你们陷在他编制的谎言中
He has you all in a net of lies.
约翰!
John!
你听起来就像是个商人在叫卖石头
You use words like a trader selling stones.
没有用心 没有爱
There's no heart to them, no love.
我有... 爱
I have... love
对那些你妄图毁灭的东西有爱...
for those things you want to destroy...
耶路撒冷城中心的神殿
the temple in the heart of Jerusalem.
流传百世的律法和传统
Centuries of law and tradition
你们这群可怜虫妄图取而代之
your pathetic little band can no more replace
却不过是螳臂当车
than a flea can fill the shoes of a man.
说简单点
Speak simply.
要是你的想法但凡有一点道理
If there is truth to your thoughts,
大家便会明白你
you'll be understood.
告诉你个简单的道理...
Here's a simple truth...
要是你站在神殿的对立面
If you set yourself against the temple,
你就会被神殿毁灭
you will be destroyed by the temple.
简单的
Simple.
道理
Truth.
就算我能说服犹太公会
Even if I could persuade the Sanhedrin
信任你的家族
to trust your family,
即使你们在我们的人民一个个
who stood by while more and more
被钉上十字架时也仅是袖手旁观
of our people were crucified.
- 我们也无计可施...  - 就算我愿意
- There was nothing...  - And even if I was willing to speak
替你辩解来获取你取代该亚法
in your defense and so gain for you
所必需的支持
the support you'll need to unseat Caiaphas
来治愈你所造成的创伤
and heal the wounds you've caused,
但你密谋反对自己的女婿
have you no shame
难道你就一点不感到羞耻?
that you'd plot against your own son-in-law?
我感到羞耻
I have shame.
为我没能早点行动
Shame that I didn't act sooner
把他们从苦痛中解救出来而羞耻
to save so many from their pain.
那些死去的人 那些像你一样
Those who died and those, like you,
失去挚爱的人
who lost the ones they loved.
我们请求你不要让这一次的失败
We ask you to not let that failing
再导致更多的流血与苦难
cost more blood and suffering,
不要错失我们可以重新开始的良机
not to let the moment pass when we can act to start afresh.
我的儿子约拿单是个正直的人
My son Jonathan is a man of integrity
会真正代表耶路撒冷的人民发声
who will truly speak for the people of Jerusalem.
是唯一一个能同时带来改变...
The only man who can bring both...
并能使之延续的人
both change and continuity.
在你把这个方案提交给彼拉多之前
Before you even think of making the case to Pilate,
得让安提帕毫无保留地支持他才行
he'll need the unreserved backing of Antipas.
彼拉多为了维护秩序 会想要他的支持
Pilate will want his approval to maintain order.
要是在你的支持下 我们能联合
If, with your support, we can unite
犹太公会的话 我们今天就可以去说服安提帕
the Sanhedrin behind us, we can approach Antipas today.
你不会后悔的 我保证
You won't regret this, I promise.
这个人要让你们相信一个被钉上十字架的弥赛亚
This man would have you believe in a crucified Messiah.
申命记里说
Deuteronomy says,
"被挂在木头上或十字架上的人
"for he that is hanged on a tree or on a cross
是在神面前受咒诅的"
is accursed of God."
但是神让他复活了
But God raised him up,
叫他摆脱了死亡的痛苦
having loosed him from the pains of death
因为他必不会被死亡所缠绕
because it was not possible he should be held by it.
你这么说而已
So you claim,
但是你们中有谁见他复活?
but who among you has seen the resurrection?
谁?
Who?
你吗?
You?
你? 还是你?
You? You?
只有这帮江湖骗子 他们需要你们相信这件事
Only your charlatans, who need you to believe it.
耶稣和他福音里的真理是蒙人所爱的
Jesus and the truth of his message are loved.
蒙世人所爱吗?
By all our people?
甚至连全耶路撒冷的人也不都爱他
Not even by all of Jerusalem.
他们根本不爱他... 他们处决了他
They loved him so little... They executed him.
然后让以赛亚的预言得以成真
And fulfilled Isaiah's prophecy.
弥赛亚多受痛苦 常经忧患
The Messiah is a man of sorrows and acquainted with grief.
这个人竟将你们所爱之人被处决
This man thinks it's a mark of success
视为胜利的标志
when those you love are executed.
等到你们全死了 他才会开心...
He won't be happy until you're all dead...
就好像司提反
Like Stephen.
你要再多呆一秒钟
If you stay here one moment longer,
我发誓我要把你的头拧下来
I swear I'm going to tear your head off.
别担心
Don't worry.
我已经听明白了 讲道理是没法把你们
I've heard enough to see that reason won't break you
从痴心妄想中解救出来的
from your delusions.
不过你还会再见到我的
You will see me again, though.
等着瞧吧
Be sure of that.
迦玛列拉比
Rabbi Gamaliel,
为何沙漠里那群亵渎神明之人
how can these blasphemers in the desert
想让这一切都结束?
want to end all this?
别操心他们了
Don't concern yourself with them.
专注你自己的研究
Look to your own studies.
提高你的悟性 然后...
Improve your understanding, and then...
没错 但他们就是看不到
Yes, but they just don't see
这些... 这一切...
that this... all of this...
就是耶路撒冷的精髓与灵魂之所在
is the heart and soul of Jerusalem.
我试过告诉他们 但他们就是不明白事理
I tried to tell them, but they just won't see reason.
那么 扫罗 别把你的精力浪费在
Then, Saul, don't spend more of your energy
试图矫正他们的错误上
trying to correct their mistake.
我能看见你从学者到拉比的晋升之路
I see a path for you from scholar to rabbi,
也许还能从拉比晋升到犹太公会里去
from rabbi to, perhaps, a seat on the Sanhedrin.
谁知道呢?
Who knows?
这些人
These men,
他们和犹太公会所做的是一件事
they do the same work as the Sanhedrin.
他们干苦工 来保护这些古老的东西
They toil to preserve the old
将之修缮一新
while making it new.
而那个渔夫彼得还有那帮子人
What this fisherman Peter and the others want to do
只想毁掉旧东西
is destroy the old,
以新代之
replace it with the new.
我得想办法阻止他们
I have to find a way to stop them.
我必须这么做
I have to.
刚才那番话谈得不错
I think that went well.
送给您的
For you.
周年纪念礼物
An anniversary gift.
您离开后
After you left our house,
我夫人提醒我 正是在十年前的普珥节
my wife reminded me that it was at Purim 10 years ago
我们第一次见面
that we first met.
我作为大祭司
Me as high priest,
而您则是加利利和佩里亚的领主
you as tetrarch of Galilee and Peraea.
彼此都想理解对方的所作所为
Each trying to work the other out.
而如今的我们仍在就此努力
And here we are, still trying.
请坐
Please.
这么说 你的岳父和他儿子
So, your father-in-law and his son
十分想要从你手里拿走
would very much like to take from you
你所穿的这套华丽的公职袍服
those fine robes of office that you wear.
现在...
Now...
你准备怎么对付
what are you going to do
沙漠里那帮信徒?
about these fanatics in the desert?
这帮狂徒的首领 他们所追随的那个人
The ringleader of the cult, the man they follow,
来自加利利
is from Galilee.
这可让我颜面尽失
This reflects very badly on me.
追随他们所谓的弥赛亚
They will soon tire of the hardships
所吃的苦头很快就会让他们放弃的
that come from following their... Messiah.
但会发生什么事呢?
But what happens?
异见变成起义
Dissent becomes revolt.
罗马帝国的回应可能会是灾难性的
The Roman response could be devastating.
替我解决掉这件事吧 该亚法
Solve this problem for me, Caiaphas.
要是他们想推翻你的事报到彼拉多那
And if this attempt to overthrow you reaches Pilate,
我会支持你的
you will have my support.
我们知道你
We know you're conspiring
和我的父亲及兄长有所密谋
with my father and brother.
我不明白你在说什么?
Should I know what you're talking about?
你们三个人是赢不了这场斗争的
The three of you won't win this fight.
我的丈夫会继续留在大祭司的位置上
My husband will remain in office as high priest,
而你会为你的背叛付出代价
and you will suffer for your betrayal.
形势开始对你丈夫不利了
Tide is turning against your husband,
我也只能顺应潮流
and I can't stand in the way of it.
如果你认识不到这一点
If you don't recognize that,
你们都会被这股浪潮所吞没
you'll both drown in the flood.
大祭司今天要处理的公务
The high priest has more to deal with today
多得你无法想象
than you can even imagine.
你觉得我应该把他带到这里
And you think that I should bring him
- 跟你说话?  - 是的
- out here to talk to you?  - Yes.
你三天之后再回来
Come back in three days.
我的回答还是一样的
The answer will still be the same,
但至少能给我时间忘掉你
but at least it'll give me chance to forget you.
三天之后 神殿面临的危险就会翻倍了
In three days, the danger to the temple could be doubled.
什么危险?
What danger to the temple?
请原谅 我...
Forgive me. I...
我只是在说那个假冒的弥赛亚的信众
I was merely talking about the followers of the false Messiah
聚集在沙漠里
gathering in the desert.
跟我来
Come with me.
你想要见我吗?
You wanted to see me?
谢谢您拨冗接见我
Thank you for your good grace.
我在神殿的藏书阁里
Having read much in the temple archives
读过很多您家族的伟大历史
of your family's great history,
我尊敬地希望...
I hope that, with respect...
我们能不能少谈一点尊敬?
Could we perhaps have a little less respect?
- 我们都有生老病死  - 当然
- Time kills us all.  - Of course.
我想我们有一个相同的利益
I believe we share a common interest,
一个相同的渴望
a common desire
帮耶路撒冷除掉一个害虫...
to rid Jerusalem of a pest...
那群渔夫和他们的追随者
The fishermen and their followers
在城墙之外
growing in numbers and confidence
默默地不断壮大
outside the city walls.
那你为何这么迫切希望让他们消失呢?
And what is it that fuels your desire to see them gone?
他们惹恼我了
They offend me.
他们想摧毁神殿的行径
Their actions to undermine the temple,
他们的挑衅行为惹恼我了
their defiance offends me.
他们对犹太公会的蔑视
Their defiance of the Sanhedrin,
犹太公会本应该执行更严厉的裁决
who could not have been more definitive in their verdict
当他们说...
when they said...
你到底想要什么?
What exactly do you want?
您授权... 我代表您行动
The authority to... act on your behalf
去解决这个问题...
and solve this problem...
把这些渎神者彻底扫除
To remove these blasphemers so completely
只言片语也不能留下
that not even the stain of their memory is left behind.
我就是忍不住想起司提反
I just can't stop thinking about Stephen.
别这样了
Stop being such a man.
什么?
What?
你看到那些在葬礼上的女人了吗?
You see the women at the funeral?
她们哭泣 她们哀嚎
They weep and they wail
把她们的痛苦都喊出来
and they scream out their pain
让全世界都知道
so the whole world knows about it.
在这些人敞开心胸表达哀恸的时候
And while all this openhearted grieving goes on,
男人们却低头看着脚
the men look at their feet
一副愁眉苦脸的样子
and put on their sad face.
不要闷在心里
Don't bottle it up.
把痛苦释放出来
Let out that pain.
彼得 领导我们才是纪念司提反最好的方式
Honor Stephen by leading us, Peter.
我需要您授予我权力
What I need is for you to give me the authority
和最低级的神殿守卫一样大的权力就行
you would give the least promoted of your temple guard.
你要怎么用这个权力?
Authority to use how?
我还要二十个神殿守卫
And 20 men from that guard.
- 啊!  - 他们的力量就在于他们很受拥戴
- Aah!  - Their strength is their popularity.
我要把这个夺走
I want to take that from them.
你们心中有疑问
You have questions.
你们说 "为什么他称我为他的磐石?"
You say, "why did he call me his rock?"
你们问 "我是那个根基吗?"
You ask, "am I the foundation?"
"这里是建造他教会的地方吗?"
"Is this where his church will be built?"
这里只有一块作根基的石头
There is only one foundation stone.
他的姓名便是耶稣基督!
And his name is Jesus Christ!
他的教会也不在这里
And his church is not here.
不在于那些帐篷 或是这些高墙
It's not in those tents or these walls.
而在于你们... 你们所有人
It's you... all of you.
你们便是他的教会
You are his church.
就像那些就算没有亲眼见他复活
And like those we ask to believe
我们也要让其相信的人一样
even though they didn't see him rise again,
即使面前是刀山火海
we must push away our fear
我们仍要无畏前行
even as we recognize the persecution we face.
我们必须去耶路撒冷 去传他的道
We have to go to Jerusalem and preach the word
去建造起他的教会!
to build his church!
你自己招人
Recruit your own men.
我来付钱
I'll pay.
恕我冒昧
Forgive me,
但如果大家看到是您在主持这项工作
but wouldn't it benefit your authority
不是更有利于您的权威吗?
to be seen as the hand at work?
我们要从掌管神殿的家族
We need to claim back the true message of our faith
和他们所听命的罗马大人那里
from the families of the temple
还原我们信仰之道的本来面目
and their masters from Rome.
他们钉死的那个人曾对你们说
They crucified the man who said to you,
"我是世上的光
"I am the light of the world.
跟从我的 就不在黑暗里走"
Whoever follows me won't walk in darkness."
我亲眼看到了他
And with my own eyes, I saw him.
我们刚刚埋葬了一个人... 他是一个好人 一个朋友
We just buried a man... a good man and a friend.
就因为他勇敢说出了真理而被乱石砸死
Stoned to death because he dared speak the truth.
他是一个年轻人 就像你们一样
He was a young man, like you.
他会流血 会痛苦 就像你们一样
He shed blood and felt pain, just like you.
他的母亲为他哭泣 就像你们的妈妈一样
His mother wept tears for him, just as yours would.
但是他迫切地想要
But he had a burning need
说出神口中的真理
to speak the truth of the word of God.
代表大祭司该亚法
With the authority of high priest Caiaphas,
我 大数人扫罗
I, Saul of Tarsus,
指控这里所有人拥护亵渎神灵者!
hereby accuse all the people here of supporting blasphemy!
你们看到了吗?
Do you see this?
这些罗马的朋友站在我们的对立面上
These friends of Rome standing against us.
这就是你的答案吗? 暴力?
Is this your answer? Violence?
你低估我了
You underestimate me.
你们都会被带走
You will all be taken away
你们的名字会被写在罪犯名单里!
and your name added to a list of offenders!
这些人什么都没有做
These people have done nothing.
如有再犯
Any further offense,
你们都将面临犹太公会的审判!
and you will all face the Sanhedrin court!
那带走我们吧 写我们的名字
Then take us. Take our names.
你们要逮捕的人是我们
We're the ones to arrest.
不 你们两个人可以走了
No. You two can go.
这些人很快就会认识到你们的危险性
These people will soon learn the danger of your company.
你和你的人根本比不过
You and your men are no match
我们心中填满的圣灵之火
for the fire of the Holy Spirit that fills us.
真的吗?
Really?
好吧 那就让我们瞧瞧谁的火更旺 怎么样?
Well, let's see whose fire burns brightest, shall we?
全部带走!
Take them!
我已经把那群狂热分子孤立起来了
I've weakened these fanatics by isolating them,
让他们的追随者与他们反目
by turning their supporters against them.
还让耶路撒冷的民众人心惶惶
By terrorizing the citizens of Jerusalem.
呃 这个问题好像没有人能解决
Well, there was a problem nobody seemed able to solve.
你也没有
Neither have you.
他们知道如果在耶路撒冷听人布道
They know you'll persecute them
会受到你的迫害
if they listen to the preachers in Jerusalem,
所以他们选择离开
so they're leaving the city
去听他们要说的话
to hear what they have to say.
你真的觉得这个扫罗
Did you really think this man Saul
会妨碍我们的使命吗?
would stand in the way of our mission?
神殿不会容忍这件事的
The temple won't stand for this.
他们不会让这持续太久的
They won't let it go on much longer.
看上去你这个叫扫罗的英雄
It looks like your hero Saul
解决不了拿撒勒人营地的问题
couldn't solve the problem of the Nazarene camp.
你那两个同谋呢?
Where are the other two conspirators?
我不是来和你抬杠的
I didn't come to bicker.
我是来请你表现出一点尊严
I came to ask you to show some dignity,
认清楚犹太公会
to recognize that the will of the Sanhedrin
已经开始反对你了
is turning against you,
请你 为了这个家族的利益
and ask you, for the good of this family,
退位吧
to stand down.
为了这个家族的利益?
For the good of this family?
为了这个家族的利益
For the good of this family,
你 当初当大祭司的时候
you, who in his day as high priest
没有和罗马统一步调的智慧
hadn't the wits to walk in step with Rome.
你 留下来一个烂摊子让我收拾
You, who left a mess behind him that I had to clear up,
你 竟敢密谋反对我?
you plot against me?
我现在还得听一个失败的糟老头子
And now I must listen to the rantings
对着我夸夸其谈
of a failed and a bitter old man
讲什么为了家族的利益?
for the good of this family?
滚出我的房子!
Get out of my house!
要不然我就会忘了你是我妻子的父亲
Before I forget you're my wife's father
然后一刀捅进你的肋骨
and put a blade between your ribs.
我们会上报给彼拉多的
We'll take this to Pilate.
比起该亚法的连襟 你一定更喜欢该亚法
You must favor Caiaphas over his brother-in-law.
一定吗?
Must I?
不要对我指手画脚
Don't tell me what to do.
十年的联盟
A 10-year-old alliance
可不能随便弃之如敝屣
shouldn't be tossed aside without good cause.
你究竟是支持该亚法 还是他夫人?
Is it Caiaphas you approve of or his wife?
我听说你们两个变得
I hear the two of you are becoming
可亲近了
the best of friends.
密涅瓦 智慧女神
Minerva, goddess of wisdom.
密涅瓦
Minerva,
这两人究竟谁该做大祭司一职
which of these men shall be high priest,
又是谁该被弃之沙漠任其腐朽呢?
and which one shall be left to rot in the desert?
什么都没有
Nothing.
真叫人失望
Very disappointing.
有传言说
There is a rumor
你早知道有人要刺杀我 却毫无作为
you knew of the plot against my life and did nothing.
是真的吗?
Is that true?
不 荒谬之极
No. That's ridiculous.
还有传言你在我宫殿里安插了眼线
And a rumor you have a spy here in my palace.
还有传言说你每晚都去拜访拿撒勒人的营地
And another that you visit the Nazarene's camp each night
同他们一起祈祷
and pray with them.
如上所述这些都表明
All of which, it's been suggested,
你不再适合继续担任公职
makes you unfit to continue in office.
这些传言有一样是真的吗?
Is any of this true?
全都不是
None of it.
都是那些想毁我清誉的人传出去的谣言
Lies are being spread by those who wish to undermine me.
毁你名声的是你自己 你没能控制住...
You undermine yourself by failing to get a grip on...
够了
Enough.
我可没时间浪费在分辨对错上
I will not waste my time separating truth from fiction,
又不是当妈的给争吵的小孩评理
like a mother with squabbling children.
该让提庇留(罗马皇帝)来决定
Tiberius shall decide.
有一次我遇到过一个希腊人 他决定一切事情
I met a Greek once who made every decision
都靠抛掷硬币
with the toss of a coin.
帝王的头像...
Emperor's head...
还是神圣的莉薇娅(提庇留的母亲)?
or the divine Livia?
我是该表彰你的雄心呢?
Shall I commend you for your ambition?
还是该谴责你散播无凭无据的谣言?
Or do I condemn you for spreading baseless rumors?
头像 我谴责你
Heads, I condemn.
莉薇娅 我表彰你
Livia, I commend.
是头像
Heads.
那么我谴责你
Then I condemn you
错漏百出的背叛行径
for making such a poor job of your treachery.
那些渔夫和他们的追随者...
These fishermen and their followers...
处理好了吗?
Are they being dealt with?
已经果断处理 永无后患了
They are, firmly and finally.
除非是妄想受所有人拥戴
Unless he wants to be loved by all,
否则大祭司一职并不难做
the high priest's job is not a hard one.
他必须要实现
He must deliver what's expected
罗马帝国对犹太省的期望
of the province of Judea by Rome
并且抵御住他的人民
and resist the many, often irrational,
无理的需索
demands of his people.
厨房里的女佣就能做到
There are girls in the kitchen who can do that.
街上的狗也能做到
Dogs in the street.
甚至一头驴也行
Even a donkey.
头像 你就留下
Heads, you stay.
莉薇娅...
Livia...
我就找头驴代替你
I'll replace you with a donkey.
捡起来好吗 该亚法?
Get that, will you, Caiaphas?
头像
Head.
好极了
Excellent.
你们俩可以退下了
You both may go.
我要同你们的大祭司说话
I need to speak with your high priest.
教你们一课
And the lesson is,
要是没手腕 就别搞政治游戏
don't play politics unless you're good at it.
这枚硬币...
This coin...
两面都是头像
It has two heads.
没错 不是吗?
It does, doesn't it?
奉仍居大祭司一职的该亚法之命
By order of Caiaphas, who remains high priest,
你从犹太公会中除名了
you are removed from the Sanhedrin.
即使是你的亲生父亲和亲兄弟
Even though it was your own father and brother
搞出这场变故吗?
who hatched this plot?
你必须离开耶路撒冷
And you will leave Jerusalem
否则就以叛国罪逮捕你
or find yourself arrested for treason.
这一切的起因正是
This all began
因为杀了那个拿撒勒人... 耶稣
with the murder of the Nazarene... Jesus.
你从旁干扰 玩弄诡计
All your interfering, your scheming.
会让你垮台的... 最终一定会
It will bring you down... eventually.
我试过跟他们讲道理
I tried to reason with them,
但他们就是不肯听
but they just wouldn't listen.
我试着把他们和追随者隔离开
I tried to come between them and their supporters,
最终却发现他们更愿意听从
but it would appear they would prefer
那个拿撒勒人愚蠢的教义
the idiotic doctrine of the Nazarene.
这封信让你全权处理除掉他们的事
This gives you my full authority to rid me of them.
永久有效
Permanently.
用尽一切办法
Do whatever is necessary.
不择手段
Whatever is necessary.
让我来告诉你们 那些人
Let me tell you about these people.
那些人想要拆毁神殿...
These people want to bring down the temple...
神殿啊
The temple.
那可是你我生命的指引
The guiding hand in yours and my life.
是智慧的源泉
The well of wisdom.
而他们以为没人...
And they think nobody...
没人... 能阻止他们
Nobody... will stand in their way.
犹太公会裁决他们亵渎神灵
They disregard the ruling of the Sanhedrin,
他们却漠然视之!
who call them blasphemers!
就在第二天
The very next day,
他们其中一人居然大摇大摆走入神殿
one of them walked into the temple itself
满口亵渎神明
proclaiming his profanity.
而且即使...
And although...
即使耶路撒冷的人民
And although the people of Jerusalem
主持了公义 将他乱石砸死
delivered their justice and they stoned him to death,
他们还是继续招募那些心智软弱的愚民
they continue recruiting the gullible and the weak-minded
参与他们的事业
to their cause.
是不是够了?
Do we say enough?
够了!
Enough!
我们要不要砍掉他们的头?
Will we break their heads?
用刀剑
With swords
用棍棒 用自己的拳头
and clubs and bare fists,
我们要告诉他们"滚出这片土地
we will say, "leave this land,
否则就让你们的血染红大地!"
or you will leave this earth in a shroud of blood!"
拿起武器! 拿起护具!
Grab weapons! Grab armor!
跟我来!
Follow me!
大家听好了 都传出话去
Pay heed to this and spread the word.
这些人被逮捕 是因为帮助 庇护
These people are being arrested for aiding, sheltering,
和喂养那个假冒弥赛亚的信众
and feeding the followers of the false Messiah.
他们会被...
They will be...
会被关押起来
They will be imprisoned.
任何人有相同行径
Anyone else who does likewise
同样将付出自由的代价
will also pay with their freedom.
还有 别想着跑去沙漠里
And don't think of scurrying off to the desert
向你们的朋友求救
for help from your friends.
下一个就轮到他们
It's their turn next.
他来了!
He's coming!
扫罗回来了!
Saul's coming back!
他的随从手里有武器
He's bringing men with swords.
尽量拿上行李!
Take what you can!
让大家赶快离开这里
Let's get everyone out of here.
这边 走 跟他们一块走
This way. Go. Go with them.
我们应该回加利利去
We should go back to Galilee.
不 我们必须一起留下来
No, we have to stay together.
我们在耶路撒冷碰头
We gather again in Jerusalem.
我们必须现在就走
We have to go now.
不 我要留下来
No. I'll stay.
我才不会被这个男人和他的威胁所吓倒
I will not be cowed by this man and his threats.
我不会让你一个人去面对
I won't leave you to face him alone.
他不是一个人
He won't be alone.
这是我的土地 我要留下来
This was my land. I'm staying.
还有我
And me.
待客之道可不止一种
There's more than one way to welcome a visitor.
我们耶路撒冷见
See you in Jerusalem.
快一点 快跑
Please hurry. Run.
小心混合
Mix it carefully.
要是太多就起不了作用了
Too much and it won't work.
走 快一点
Go. Move faster.
快走 再快点
Go on. Faster.
抓住我的手
Take my hand.
雅各 走
James, go.
全部拆掉
Pull it all down.
都烧掉
Burn it.
我要让这里像他们从来没来过一样
I want nothing left to show that they were ever here.
动手!
Now!
他走得太迟了
He's leaving it too late.
不
No.
他清楚他在做什么
He knows what he's doing.
那里!
There!
抓住他!
Take him!
现在来瞧瞧究竟谁的火烧得更旺!
Let's see whose fire burns brightest now!
不!
No!
不!!
No!!
我要毁了你!
I will crush you!
尽管放马过来!
You will try!
放马过来!